# Marc Girons Lopez

Address Oberwiesen

Birth

Oberwiesenstrasse 50

8050 Zurich (Switzerland) 5 September 1986

Barcelona (Spain)

Website Telephone

ephone +41 (0) 78-775 89 93 E-mail gironslopez@gmail.com

gironslopez.me

Citizenship Spain

I am a hydrologist with an interdisciplinary background working as postdoctoral researcher at the University of Zurich. I aim at contributing to build up knowledge and understanding about water related issues to make society more resilient and sustainable. I believe in continuous learning and communication and I am also interested in societal behaviour and data analysis. Everything is connected!

## **Professional Experience**

feb 2017 — aug 2018 Postdoctoral Researcher • University of Zurich (Switzerland)

My research focuses on improving the realism of the snow routine of the HBV rainfall-runoff model while maintaining a low model uncertainty.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Teaching Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Lecturing, leading seminars, and leading and assisting in laboratory and field

activities for both undergraduate and graduate courses.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Research Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Design and implementation of hydrology research projects within hydrology, including defining research questions, modelling, data analysis, and

reporting scientific results.

jun 2009 — aug 2009 — Quality Control Intern · Laboratori Català de Control (Spain)

Quality control tests of cement, concrete and anchorages. Tests of soil properties, water sampling and analysis. Defining procedures for adopting ISO

rules.

jul 2008 — sep 2008 Environmental Consultant Intern • URS Corporation (Spain)

Environmental control tests of petrol stations, soil decontamination, and hydrogeological data processing. Fauna and sediment sampling for the quality

control of rivers and dams.

## Education

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Hydrology and Water Resources Science

Thesis: Information Needs for Water Resource and Risk Management:

Hydro-Meteorological Data Value and Non-Traditional Information.

aug 2009 — jun 2011 Master of Science (MSc) · Uppsala University (Sweden)

Earth Sciences (Hydrology/Hydrogeology)

Thesis: Modelling Climatic and Hydrological Variability in Lake Babati, North-

ern Tanzania.

sep 2004 — jun 2009 Bachelor of Science (BSc) · Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (Spain)

Geology

aug 2007 — jun 2008 Exchange student • Université Joseph Fourier (Grenoble I) (France)

Geology and Earth Sciences

#### **Selected Publications**

(A comprehensive list of publications can be found on the website.)

**Girons Lopez, M.**, Di Baldassarre, G., and Seibert, J. (2017). "Impact of social preparedness on flood early warning systems". In: *Water Resources Research* 53.1, pp. 522-534. ISSN: 1944-7973. DOI: 10.1002/2016WR019387.

**Girons Lopez, M.** and Seibert, J. (2016). "Influence of hydro-meteorological data spatial aggregation on streamflow modelling". In: *Journal of Hydrology* 541, pp. 1212–1220. ISSN: 0022-1694. DOI: 10.1016/j.jhydrol.2016.08.026.

**Girons Lopez, M.**, Wennerström, H., Nordén, L.-Å., and Seibert, J. (2015). "Location and Density of Rain Gauges for the Estimation of Spatial Varying Precipitation". In: *Geografiska Annaler: Series A, Physical Geography* 97.1, pp. 167–179. ISSN: 1468-0459. DOI: 10.1111/geoa.12094.

#### Skills

Programming Python • Matlab • LATEX • Fortran

**Software** ArcGIS • QGIS • HBV • Git • Inkscape • Linux

**Instrumentation** Campbell data loggers • hydro-meteorological sensors

**Languages** Native Catalan • Spanish

Full professional proficiency English

Professional working proficiency Swedish • French

**Elementary proficiency** German

Other Swedish driving license (B)

## Grants, Awards, & Honours

2017 Travel grant • Swiss Association of Geography

2016 Photo contest winner • EGU
2015 Research Fellowship • CUAHSI
2014 Travel grant • Liljewalchs Foundation

2007 Scholarship • Swedish-Spanish Foundation

2007 Scholarship • Erasmus Programme

## Other Activities

2016 — 2017 Translator • Planet Press

I translate short scientific articles for kids from the European Geosciences

Union (EGU) Planet Press initiative from English to Spanish.

2013 Volunteer • IAHS

I volunteered supporting the organisation of the 2013 IAHS, IAPSO, IAPSEI

Joint Assembly in Gothenburg (Sweden).